WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Welcome to the finale of
Survivor: Winners at War.
Now, normally, on a finale
night, we're in Los Angeles,
we're live, we're all together,
packed house full of
screaming Survivor fans,
giant Tribal Council
and some really great energy.
But for obvious reasons,
we can't do that tonight.
So instead,
we're in my garage.
For real.
The amazing
Survivor art department
designed a Tribal Council set
and they shipped it to me
in these two huge crates--
this was in pieces,
I mean, brick by brick--
along with a instruction guide,
basically a-a manual
for how to build
a Tribal Council for dummies--
me being the dummy--
that would allow me
to build this in my garage.
Yes, I might have had a little
help from our 16-year-old.
But we've had
a great time doing it.
They also shipped out
the cameras, a couple of lights,
and FaceTime,
getting them set up.
There are no camera operators.
We're using our home Internet
to transmit.
This is my daily EarPod
that I use for sports.
That's the microphone.
People ask if Survivor is real.
Come on.
This is as real as it gets.
And it's the perfect way
to end this fantastic season,
so let's get into it.
This was the biggest season
we'd ever done.
20 winners, $2 million prize,
the introduction of fire tokens,
the return of
the Edge of Extinction,
and gameplay that has
truly taken Survivor
to the next level.
And I've heard from so many
of you, so many Survivor fans,
so many Survivor families, that
I know are watching tonight,
saying, week after week,
"This is the greatest season
of all time."
I agree. I think this is the
greatest season we've ever done.
And for a show that has been on
for 20 years and 40 seasons,
it really is saying something.
And all credit goes
to the players.
They did this.
Put 'em up there.
They deserve all of the praise.
20 returning winners
who battled all season.
There they are,
safe and sound at home tonight.
Nice to get a little peek
into their world.
They'll be watching with their
family, loved ones, friends,
as we bring this season
to a close.
So I hope you are ready
for a packed finale,
because this is-- it's epic.
It is dramatic.
It's emotional.
It's unpredictable.
There is so much story going on,
we don't have time
for a reunion show.
It is that packed. You'll see.
And at the end of the night,
we'll be right here.
We'll have the urn
with the votes.
We have Zoom set up
for the final three.
And we will crown the champion
of Survivor: Winners at War,
which comes with
huge bragging rights--
are they the best of all time?--
and $2 million
for their efforts.
So let's set it up.
We have our final five:
Sarah, Ben, Tony,
Michele, Denise.
Then we have
the Edge of Extinction,
where everybody,
with the exception of Sandra,
is still in it.
They're gonna battle
in one challenge.
One of them will
get back in the game.
This is why they've been living
out there, for this one shot.
That person will make
the final six.
And from that point forward,
I promise you it's a beautiful
but bloody battle to the end.
So buckle up. Here we go.
The finale of
Survivor: Winners at War.
♪ ♪
Come on in, guys!
All right.
Final five.
Today you will not compete.
Today you watch.
Come on in, guys!
♪ ♪
Returning from the Edge
of Extinction for the last time.
Edge of Extinction
started 33 days ago
with Natalie, first person
voted out on day two.
One after another, you were
voted out and sent to the Edge,
waiting for this moment
right here,
a chance to earn your way
back into this game
with a legit shot
at the title of Sole Survivor
and the $2 million prize
at stake.
This is that moment.
Let's get to it.
For today's challenge,
you'll be attached to a rope.
On my go, you'll race
through a fence obstacle
and then a post obstacle.
You'll then dig up a rope rung
and use it
to build a rope bridge.
You'll then race to the end,
where you must maneuver
two balls through a table maze.
First person to land both their
balls earns their way back in.
This is the moment.
Let's see what you do with it.
Take your spots.
We'll get it on.
Here we go. Good luck.
♪ ♪
All right, during your time
on Extinction,
you worked hard for a shot
at earning some advantages.
Natalie, Parvati,
Yul and Wendell
bought the first advantage.
They will skip the fence
obstacle and start at the post.
Natalie also bought
the second advantage,
which allows her
to skip the dig.
Her rope rung will be waiting
for her at the rope bridge.
She also bought
the third advantage,
which means one-third
of her rope bridge
is already assembled.
Big advantages.
Let's see what you do with them.
Here we go.
Survivors ready?
Go!
It is on.
This is it,
your return challenge.
Out of the gate, four people
have the first advantage.
Everybody else is gonna
run the entire course.
(grunting)
Yul is through quickly.
He's out first.
Yul can start digging.
Parvati right behind him.
Wendell is through.
He can start digging.
(grunting)
Everybody else
launching themselves
through this first obstacle.
Natalie, who has
all three advantages,
is stuck in the first section
she has to run.
It is costing her a lot of time.
She cannot get through.
Wendell is through. He can start
working on his rope bridge.
Boston Rob is through.
He's now where Natalie is.
Here comes Sophie.
Wow, what an unexpected
turn of events.
Three advantages, and she can't
get out of the first section.
Rob is through quickly.
He can start digging.
Natalie finally through.
Tyson gonna start to dig.
Natalie's good.
You skip the dig.
Natalie goes
right to the rope bridge.
It is now Natalie and Wendell
in the lead.
But a lot of people are in this.
(panting):
Okay.
(grunting)
Yul has his rope rung.
He's good.
He's working on the rope bridge.
Parvati's got hers.
It is Natalie, Parvati,
Yul and Wendell.
All four had advantages
in this challenge,
and right now
they are paying off.
Another setback for Natalie.
Rob's in it now.
Tyson staying in it.
Sophie's got hers.
We got a challenge.
It's Wendell in the lead.
Natalie right on his tail,
but she had three advantages.
Jeremy has his.
Kim has hers.
Everybody else still fighting.
Wendell is through first.
He's working on his knots,
trying to release those balls
for the table maze.
There's still
a lot of challenge left.
That table maze is tough.
Rob's getting very close.
Tyson's still in this.
No, Natalie's got to go back.
Natalie has one rope down.
She's got to go back,
re-hook it.
Another setback for Natalie.
Wendell has his two balls.
He's first to the maze.
Trying to land that first ball.
Wendell drops.
Got to go back.
Boston Rob is through.
Yul is through.
Here comes Sophie.
Jeremy's in this.
Natalie finally through.
It is Wendell's challenge
right now.
Can anybody catch him?
Wendell very close
to that first ball.
And he's got it.
Wendell has the first.
He's down to one ball left.
Natalie's through.
Rob is now at the table maze.
Here comes Yul.
Wendell in the lead
with his first ball.
After a long time on Extinction,
there's not much left
in the tank.
Everybody's using
everything they have
right now to get back
in the game.
Natalie trying
to land that first ball.
Would tie her with Wendell.
It requires a lot of touch.
And she's got it.
It is now Natalie with one
and Wendell with one.
Rob drops.
Got to start again.
Parvati drops.
Has to start again.
Tyson-- very close
to sticking that first ball.
Tyson has his first ball.
He's in it.
It is Tyson, Wendell and Natalie
trying to work their way
back in.
Wendell at a dicey part
of this maze.
He's in the finish zone.
Wendell drops.
Natalie very close.
And a tough corner.
-She's got it!
-(whoops) Oh, my God!
Natalie has earned her way
back into this game!
-(crying)
-After 33 days,
being the first person
voted out,
she is now part
of the final six.
-What a story.
-NATALIE: Thank you so much.
PROBST:
Instantly, the reality
for everybody else
starts to set in.
NATALIE:
Thank you.
PROBST:
This game is over.
Natalie, here is your new Buff.
Take your spot
with the final six.
-Thanks, guys.
-Good job, Nat.
BEN:
Hey. Good job.
So, there are
a lot of unique stories
on Survivor over 20 years.
-Kim.
-Yeah.
You're always so good
at wrapping up your story.
So when you look back on this,
Winners at War,
what was it about?
Um, my first season,
I was told
I was perfect,
flawless, it was easy.
And this was anything but that.
I was on the outs. I could
never get a footing in the game.
I made every mistake.
And this, in a lot of ways,
was my greatest fear,
you know,
that I was gonna come out,
like, screw up everything
that I proved myself to be
the first time around.
And yet I feel...
maybe, better.
I feel really at peace
with my story here,
which was it didn't
have to be perfect.
I didn't have to win.
I'm still me.
I'm so glad
I did not say no to this.
I'm so glad that I said yes,
that my kids
got to see me say yes,
that I did it,
and that I screwed it up
and I'm going home me.
And it feels really good.
PROBST:
Tyson, if this is
the end for you,
wrap it up for me.
I mean, the last decade
has been, for me,
pretty much Survivor.
There's nothing that...
fully encompassed all the weird
talents I had as a person
more than Survivor.
Like, the first time I played,
I was like,
"This is the only job
built for me."
(laughter)
And then, you know,
I had kids, and...
...I think, for me,
that encompasses
all of my weird talents
even better than Survivor does.
I think I needed
to come out here
and struggle
and play from the bottom.
I've never had to do that.
And I think I kind of needed it
to know I don't need it.
I think being a dad,
for me, is a good replacement
for Survivor.
PROBST:
Amber,
why are you out here?
(sniffling):
I didn't come here for me.
I only came here for one person,
and I came here for him.
(both sniffling)
Nobody respects this game
more than my husband does.
I wanted to be here for him.
I wanted to be his rock.
I never thought
I had a chance in hell
to win this time around,
because...
...even when you read my name
as the All-Star winner,
I knew that...
nobody really felt like
I deserved it.
Everybody felt
that this guy deserved it,
and the only reason why
they voted for me is because
they hated him
more than they hated me.
(laughter)
ROB:
But if there's any lesson
I want to take away from this,
we came out here
to show our kids
you try, you don't quit,
you don't give up,
and you do your best.
And their mother's the
toughest woman in this world.
She stayed out there
that whole time,
made rice for everybody
every single day,
never complained.
This is a woman
that's a champion.
(applause)
188 days for me.
-ADAM: Wow.
-But I leave here with nothing
but love for everybody,
gratitude and appreciation.
Thank you.
PROBST:
Parvati,
you came back to play again
after just giving birth.
Why did you come back?
Where was the gas in the tank
coming from?
(Parvati chuckles)
Um...
Yeah, I didn't have
much gas in the tank.
When you called me and
you were asking me to come back,
I was like, "No way.
You're out of your mind.
-I'm, like, so happy."
-(chuckles)
Because I'm having
this adventure
as a new mom,
with a little newborn
who's, like,
the love of my life,
who's squishy and cute.
And then there's Survivor,
which is the exact opposite
of that.
It's, like,
blindsides and deceit
and, like,
really hurting people.
Like, it's a vicious game.
I didn't know
if I had that in me,
but I was willing
to come back out here
and play this game with
every ounce of heart that I had.
And I feel like I did.
(chuckles)
(sniffles, sobs softly)
It's been a very different ride
for me this time
than it ever has before.
But I'm going back out
really proud of who I was
in this version of the game.
PROBST:
Ethan,
is it fair to ask you
about what it is like
to have literally been
to the edge in our human life
and then come out here
and play this game
that's silly on one hand
but can be transformative
on the other?
Yeah, I mean, um...
(smacks lips)
You know, Survivor: Africa
changed my life.
Because of Survivor,
we launched
Survivor Stand Up To Cancer,
which has raised millions
of dollars for cancer research.
And I don't know
if many people know this, but...
some of the money raised through
Survivor Stand Up To Cancer
helped fund the drug
that saved my life.
-Wow.
-So, not only did it,
like, create a life for me,
this show saved my life.
Not too long ago,
like, I was battling
a rare form of blood cancer,
and I just craved survival.
Like, I just wanted
to live one more day.
And I was thinking
to myself, like,
"If I get out
of this transplant alive,
I want to play Survivor."
And I prayed and I dreamed
that I could get myself
healthy enough
to be able to, like,
come out here and play again.
And I did.
For me, this is like
the perfect bookend
on this crazy and amazing life
that Survivor has gifted me.
And I'm so grateful and honored
to be part of this crew
right here.
So I truly appreciate that.
And, uh, thank you, everyone.
-YUL: Thank you, Ethan.
-(applause)
I'd just like to say that
I think one of the reasons
Survivor is so unique
is that
we are all, sort of,
this giant weird family.
Fans who have watched for
20 years, they know you guys.
They've seen you at your bottom,
and they've seen you at the top.
And yet you continue
to come back
and share your stories with us,
and they inspire people.
-So I give it up to you guys.
-(applause)
And with that,
Edge of Extinction is over,
but your job remains the same.
You are the jury.
You'll have some more members
joining you.
But, for now,
grab your stuff, head out,
and we'll see you
at the next Tribal Council.
-(whoops)
-PARVATI: Thanks, Jeff.
-Thank you. Thank you.
-Thank you.
Good luck, guys.
PROBST:
We started with 20 of the best
that have ever played this game.
You are the final six.
And this battle
is not yet over.
Grab your stuff.
Head back to camp. I'll see you
at your next immunity challenge.
TONY:
When I seen all these people
and they're telling
their stories--
the hardships,
the suffering,
the struggling that they did
on the Edge--
it really hurt me
on an emotional level.
However, I got to put
the emotions to the side.
We have a game to play.
I'm not gonna let off the gas
for one second.
As a matter of fact, I'm gonna
press it even harder, if I can.
I'll put it right through
the floor at this time,
because the end is coming up.
That drive is what makes
these players great.
They lived on the Edge
for that one opportunity.
Natalie won, she's back in,
and now, as Tony said,
you put the pedal
through the metal.
All right, you're not
gonna hear from me again
until it's time
to read the votes,
but because we can't do
a reunion show tonight,
due to time,
we sent audio recorders
to each of the 20 players,
and we asked them to tell us,
in their own words,
what their Survivor experience
has meant to them.
Take a look.
♪ ♪
ADAM:
Being able to step
inside of the television
with my childhood heroes
means, for my life,
that anything is possible.
-...Winners at War.
-(applause)
ADAM:
It completely changed my life,
and now I believe I can do
anything I set my mind to.
MICHELE:
Come on, Adam!
-PROBST: And he's got it!
-(excited shouting)
TONY:
I'm the type of person that
I don't even leave my city.
-Don't drop it, Tony!
-So playing the game is
the most amazing experience
that I will ever have.
KIM:
It is such a hard physical
and emotional experience.
You have to know who you are
to play Survivor.
And if you don't know who you
are, you're about to find out.
MICHELE:
You transform out there
on the beach,
and it changed me
for the better.
I found my own identity.
PARVATI:
It has certainly instilled
this unquenchable thirst
for adventure in my life.
-(whooping)
-WENDELL: If you don't
have confidence,
getting to go
out on that island
and actually proving it
to yourself, that's a blessing.
-Yara wins immunity!
-(cheering)
SOPHIE:
It taught me to embrace
the parts of me that succeed,
but also the parts of me
that can fail things
and being okay with that.
NATALIE:
When I have hard times
in real life,
I always go back
to that Survivor experience,
when it seemed,
like, impossible.
YUL:
Go!
NICK:
Survivor kicked me
in the butt to get me
to that place where
I was finally grown-up.
DENISE:
It taught me
so much about life,
about what I was capable of.
YUL:
When I was a kid, I was an
incredibly introverted person.
Done. (whoops)
But winning Survivor
kind of validated
the kind of person I've grown
into, which is priceless.
SARAH:
Winning a million dollars,
especially in the Midwest,
-definitely changed my life.
-(applause, shouting)
Getting that opportunity,
I'm so fortunate.
SANDRA:
I wouldn't have
what I have today
if it wasn't for Survivor.
It is the greatest thing
I have ever done.
-(Parvati laughs)
-ETHAN: At its core is
a game of relationships.
-Ethan.
-And it's human to human,
even if we're playing
this really hard game.
-Proud of you, dude.
-Keep going, keep going.
BEN:
I grew immensely
as a human being playing.
I learned it was okay
to trust people,
and I learned
about forgiveness.
DANNI:
Survivor really took me
back to the basics
when it comes to realizing
-what's really important
in life.
-(laughing)
ROB:
When I started playing,
I was just a kid,
and now just celebrated
my 15-year wedding anniversary.
I love you.
AMBER:
Survivor has given me
everything that I value
in life,
worth way more than
the million dollars, for sure.
TYSON:
With the million dollars
comes freedom to spend
a lot of time with my children,
my family.
That's the biggest blessing.
-PROBST: And he's got it!
-Yeah!
JEREMY:
The biggest life lesson
I've taken from this:
enjoy the people
that you love...
Let's go!
...and have a deeper bond
with your family.
-Survivor has given me that.
-(crying)
You don't even
have to win the mil to--
for it to change your life.
It changes everybody's life.
Thank you.
(cheering)
JEREMY:
It's awesome.
-Thank you for the gift!
-Thank you!
♪ ♪
TONY:
Welcome to Casa Koru.
NATALIE:
I left this camp day two,
and it's unreal that
I'm even saying this, but...
I made it back on Survivor.
Like, this has been the goal
since I was first voted off.
I bet everything
on myself today,
and it paid off, because
today I'm with the final six
and feels ... amazing.
-Oh, my God!
-(Sarah chuckles)
Oh, my God, guys.
This is crazy.
The challenge
was the first hurdle.
And now I have a huge feat
in front of me
to make it to the end.
The target's on me.
This is a tight clique.
I have to create
some waves so that
wheels start churning
in people's heads
to turn on anybody but me.
Luckily, it's only me here,
so I can tell any lie
of Extinction I want.
But I got to keep my lies
straight.
-BEN: Yeah.
-NATALIE: I think everybody's
kind of obsessed with Tony.
Everybody's on
the Tony bandwagon there.
I'm just sick of it.
And the old-school people--
basically,
the impression is that
Tony's doing everything
and everybody else
-is just taking instructions.
-TONY: What?
TONY:
You have somebody like Natalie
coming into this
from the Edge;
it's very tricky.
It's very dangerous
for my game,
'cause she can say
whatever she wants to us.
That information
could be total lies,
because nobody's here
from the Edge to debunk it.
And she started blowing up
people's spots,
especially mine. She's like,
"Oh, everybody loves you, Tony.
"Uh, you're-you're their
favorite. You're-you're gonna--
You're-you're the winner
in their eyes."
And I'm like, uh,
you know what, this is no good.
I hope nobody believes that.
I-I mean, deep down inside,
I hope it's true.
But I hope nobody
believes that, because
I don't want her to put
this target on my back
that I don't need right now.
It's poison.
SARAH:
Mm-mm.
TONY:
Yeah.
-I don't know.
-I don't know her enough.
But if-if somebody
takes her to the end,
she wins,
if she gets to the end, no?
-You think-- No.
-No?
-No.
-Oh, my. See?
If you're thinking like that,
so is Ben.
-I know. But he won't turn.
-I'm not thinking like that.
-No, I know,
but I'm not thinking like that.
-And I'm not turning, so...
If she goes to the Edge,
that's an accomplishment.
She stayed there
the whole 39 days.
That's such a backstory.
-Mm-hmm.
-She made it through.
She didn't eat
so she could get advantages
-to get back in the game.
-Mm-hmm.
She struggled.
She suffered.
-She came back and won.
-Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm.
-No, I get that.
-So...
SARAH:
I've never played with Natalie,
so I don't know
how savvy she is.
She's telling everybody that
the jury's gonna vote for Tony.
Is that a ploy to get me
to vote Tony out?
Or is it truthful?
You know,
it strikes a nerve with me,
because Tony would not be here
without me.
But it doesn't matter
what I believe.
It's what the jury believes.
I feel like you wouldn't be
where you are without me,
and I feel like I wouldn't be
where I am without you.
-Yeah.
-I know the game that I played.
I know that, if you win,
you might win the money,
you might win the title,
but you wouldn't have it
without me,
and I was not your puppet.
-I know that, Sarah.
-And I know that.
SARAH:
I have to get my story out
to the jury
and make sure
that they know that women
are just as equal as men,
and just because a man
and a woman are working together
doesn't mean the man
is calling all the shots.
(birds chirping)
♪ ♪
Come on in, guys!
What the heck?
-MICHELE: Wow.
-PROBST: All right.
Let's get to
today's immunity challenge.
First things first, Michele,
gonna take it back.
(chuckles softly)
Bummer.
-Thank you.
-Thanks, Jeff.
Once again,
immunity is back up for grabs.
For today's challenge, you're
gonna race through an obstacle,
collect a bag,
then head up a tower.
You'll drop the bag
and then launch yourself
down a giant water slide.
Do it again.
Once you have all three bags,
you'll use
the pieces inside to solve
a three-tier puzzle.
First to finish
wins immunity--
safe from the vote,
guaranteed to see day 37.
Losers, Tribal Council,
where somebody will be
voted out and become
the 14th member of our jury.
-Draw for spots.
We'll get started. Let's do it.
-BEN: Yes, sir.
♪ ♪
PROBST:
Here we go.
For immunity.
Survivors ready?
Go!
The course is divided
into two halves.
It is Denise, Tony
and Sarah on one side,
Michele, Natalie
and Ben on the other,
running the same course.
Denise on the two-plank bridge.
Tony's across the disc bridge.
Ben is across the rope bridge.
Sarah across the rope bridge.
Natalie is across
the disc bridge.
Michele working
on the two-plank bridge.
Ben heading back
with his first bag.
Here comes Tony.
Sarah right behind.
Here comes Natalie
with her first.
Now you got to go up
a lot of steps
and then slide down
and do it again.
Heading up those steps
on day 36,
that looks like Mount Everest.
Ben is on fire right now.
Tony's down,
looking for his second bag.
Here comes Natalie and Sarah,
side by side.
That's how you do it
on Survivor!
Denise is through
the two-plank bridge.
She's coming back.
It is Michele still working
on that two-plank bridge.
It does take more time.
Everybody has to do it.
Here comes Ben with his second.
-(exhales)
-PROBST: Denise has
her first bag.
She's heading down the slide.
Tony with his second.
Here comes Natalie
with her second.
Ben out of control,
going sideways.
Landing nicely.
-I give it a ten.
-(chuckles)
Michele has her first bag.
Let's go, Michele.
Here comes Tony.
Not pretty. Doesn't matter.
Natalie coming back down.
Michele tries to stay in it.
Denise coming back
with her second bag.
Sarah right behind her.
-Woo-hoo!
-Here comes Michele.
-Ah!
-She's through.
-(panting)
-Sarah heading back down
for the second time
on the slide.
Here comes Denise
right behind.
We got a challenge
going on here.
Ben untying his third
and final bag.
He's got it.
Ben will get to the top first.
He can start working
on that puzzle.
Tony has his third bag.
Michele with her second.
Natalie with her third
and final bag.
Natalie gonna get in
on the puzzle.
She's gonna lap Michele
heading up those steps.
That is what it takes,
is a second,
third, fourth burst of energy
on Survivor.
Denise and Sarah coming back
with that third and final bag.
You're still in it, Michele.
You know this puzzle.
Yes, I do, Jeff.
Michele did this puzzle,
and she won.
That could be the difference.
But she's got to get
that third and final bag.
-Sarah back with her third
and final bag.
-(panting)
You can see the fatigue.
Denise is to the top.
She can start working
on the puzzle.
It is everybody but Michele
working on the puzzle.
It's a three-tier puzzle,
so you're looking
to measure these pieces
so they all are the same height.
That will allow you to start
building the second layer.
Here comes Michele.
Michele has untied
her third bag.
Michele heading back now.
One last ascent up these steps,
and she'll be in it.
It would be a massive comeback
for Michele to get back in this.
Looks so easy.
How difficult could it be
to get six posts to line up
at the same height?
Michele has her first tier.
That is a big advantage
right now.
Everybody looking over
to see what she did.
Y'all are a bunch of cheaters.
PROBST: Michele is trying to
make a giant comeback right now.
And, suddenly,
Natalie thinks she has
that first tier figured out.
Natalie's now in it.
Now Michele will start
to feel a little pressure.
That's okay.
PROBST: Quickly,
Natalie starts placing pieces.
Sarah now has her first tier.
Sarah's now in it.
Michele is on fire right now.
There is a theme this season
of a lot of winners feeling
they have something to prove.
Michele is proving it right now.
Very quickly,
Michele has her second tier.
Michele now starting to work
on her third and final tier.
It would be a repeat win
for immunity.
It is literally everybody
just looking
at what Michele is doing,
trying to find
the matching pieces
to just copy what she's doing.
Sarah right next door
to Michele,
just looking over.
Natalie checking
what Michele's doing.
Michele undaunted
as she continues
to move pieces around.
Michele thinks she has it.
Is she right?
That's it.
-That is it!
-(squeals)
-... yeah!
-Michele wins
individual immunity!
(laughing)
I told you it was okay.
Oh, my God.
(blows raspberry)
Michele, come on over.
(Michele chuckles)
The dance again.
You are safe tonight.
Cannot be voted out
of this game.
As for the rest of you,
got nothing for ya.
Grab your stuff. Head back to
camp. See you tonight at Tribal.
TONY:
This next Tribal's gonna be
very, very tricky.
We seen it in season 38,
where Chris comes back
from the Edge with an idol.
But I'm glad that happened,
because it opens up
people's eyes to see
that's what's gonna happen
to all of you guys.
I'm pretty nervous about that,
because if she plays
some advantage,
that could be
sending me packing,
and I don't want that
to happen.
♪ ♪
BEN:
Is that all right?
-Is that enough?
-NATALIE: Of course, take more.
-We have so much here.
-(chuckles): I know, I know.
But, like, I'm sick of rice
right now, Natalie.
-Oh, you're telling me, dude.
-(laughs)
-Let's just chill, man.
Eat this.
-NATALIE: Yeah.
I can't chill out like you guys.
You guys can chill.
I'm gonna go look for an idol.
(chuckles)
TONY: When there's a potential
problem, I'd rather try
to address it than ignore it.
'Cause when you ignore
a potential problem,
it usually bites you
in the butt.
-NATALIE: Shall I go get water?
-Yeah, yeah, go ahead.
TONY:
This is Survivor.
It's a game of the unknown.
So let's prepare
for the unknown.
-All right, I'll be back.
-It's better to
assume that she has something
than assume that she doesn't.
What do you mean? We...
It's all good.
I know. We got to figure it out,
because if she has something,
man, what's gonna happen?
There's no way she has...
I'm not gonna guarantee it,
but...
Tony's got an idol.
All he's got to do
is just play it cool tonight,
and we can make it
to the final four.
(laughs): And he's not
playing it cool right now.
We seen somebody come in
from the Edge and win, man.
-I know.
-What would two,
two, two happen?
No harm, no foul, right?
If two of us
are going Natalie, two of us
are going Denise, and those two,
whoever they vote,
it doesn't matter.
We-we break the tie
by sending Natalie home.
BEN:
A smart Survivor
would say split the votes,
but I'm not gonna do that
to Mama D right now.
Survivor for me the first time
was powering through people
and not worrying
about the human aspect.
This time, I've learned
from my first experience,
and I'm trying to grow on that
as a Survivor player
and as a human.
Denise is not a number to me.
She's a friend. She's an ally.
Anybody wants to talk to me,
I am open.
I'm trying to go with the flow,
apparently,
that you guys have here,
which is no scramble.
Everybody tells each other
everything.
-We can talk.
Do you want to talk?
-NATALIE: Yeah.
-Yeah, we can talk. Let's go.
-MICHELE: Okay. Let's do it.
NATALIE: The best-case scenario
for me not winning immunity,
which was obviously
my first choice,
is Michele winning immunity.
She's at the bottom, and, so,
at this point, my game plan
is to work with Michele
and make sure we break up
this foursome tonight.
BEN:
I mean, you think
Michele's working with her?
-TONY: She has no choice.
-What do you mean,
she has no choice?
TONY:
She has no choice
because she knows...
She'd be stupid
to work with her.
-(whispers): No!
Dude, this has been...
-And...
-Wait, let's sit.
-Now Tony's like... Yeah.
No.
And that's what I'm saying.
MICHELE:
I've been trying so hard
to shake up this game.
But it's been really hard
with Tony
and Sarah running this game.
They have been so loyal
to each other.
I have no allegiance
to any of these people.
Somebody coming in
from the Edge
and saying that
they want to work with me,
that they have an idol
and I have the necklace
around my neck
is pretty much
the ideal situation
on day 36.
All votes are
gonna go on you tonight.
We can't beat Tony.
So do we take Tony out right now
with an idol and...
-Tony's gonna play his idol.
-He is?
NATALIE:
If I pull out an idol
at Tribal,
-he's gonna play his for him.
-MICHELE: Yeah.
NATALIE:
The only thing
I really know for sure
is that Michele
is safe tonight,
I have an idol,
and it's about time
we shook this foursome up.
So I'm so thankful
that I held out on that idol
and I brought it in the game
with me,
because if not,
I would be going home tonight.
Yeah.
MICHELE:
Actually,
we just basically said, like,
"I'm gonna throw my vote
on Tony."
-Okay, good.
-But...
-Does she have an idol?
I don't know.
She seems paranoid right now,
so if she did,
she's voting Tony.
-Yeah.
-I don't know.
-TONY: Okay.
-BEN: She's probably gonna
vote me.
If she stands up
and plays an idol tonight,
-I'm gonna have to play mine.
-TONY: You don't want
to do some splitting
so you don't have to waste
the idol, man? 'Cause
tomorrow's the last day, man.
-I don't.
-But, damn, do I have
to do it, too, man?
'Cause I think they're
making me flush mine out.
I would think
Ben would be all for saving
his idol so we can guarantee
ourselves in the final four.
It's mind-boggling
how everybody's so reluctant
to throw any votes on Denise.
They're adamant that this girl
Natalie does not have anything.
-I don't think she's got one.
-No.
So I-I think
we're-we're spinning our wheels
on this and doing a lot
of coulda, woulda, shouldas.
-BEN: Mm-hmm.
-TONY: If Natalie stands up
and plays an idol,
now I go into panic mode.
You, Ben, go into panic mode.
We burn our idols.
Natalie's safe,
and either Sarah
or Denise are on the
chopping block at that point.
So let's just get rid of Denise
and be safe.
It's a win-win.
I want me. I want you.
I want Ben. We vote Denise.
And keep Natalie?
-If she has an idol...
-She doesn't.
SARAH:
Tony started freaking out
that Natalie
might have an idol.
I have to always tell him,
"Would you just trust me?
Calm down."
That's all I do,
and that's what
people don't realize.
Why take a chance
for me to blow my idol,
Ben to blow his idol,
and-and then
you possibly going home?
-We move on
for another day to fight.
-She don't have an idol.
SARAH:
Natalie doesn't have an idol.
You know why?
Because Natalie and I,
in the one day she's been here,
have built a good enough bond
that Natalie would've told me
if she had something.
-Sarah, please, think about it.
-Well, damn it, Tony.
-But I'm telling you, though.
-Okay.
-Okay, that's it, then. If...
-I get what you're saying.
-If you're 100%, then that's it.
-I'm 100%.
-Boom. Done.
-SARAH: Welcome to my world.
I've lived 36 days
of trying to calm Tony down.
These girls
don't have anything,
so calm down, dude.
Guess who's in control? Sarah.
Sarah knows what's going on.
♪ ♪
PROBST:
All right. Ben,
is the elephant in the room
the Edge of Extinction
returning player
and the threat that holds?
BEN:
I would say so, Jeff.
She's been able
to sit over there
with a lot of these folks
and make a lot of friendships
while we've been away
hacking at each other,
and that's part of the strategy
that comes into play.
PROBST:
So, Michele,
the easy vote would be
for the five of you
to just simply say, "Look,
we can all just stay together
-and get rid of her."
-MICHELE: Well, the reality
of the situation is
that somebody new comes in.
They bring in new information.
There's a lot to digest
with what they're saying
that the jury is saying.
And, so, we knew
the chaos was gonna come,
but it hit us all
in different ways.
But normally,
you have someone to back-check
and-and follow up on a story.
With Miss Nat here,
there's no fact-checking.
We have to take everything
that she says for her word.
And she's good at what she does.
She stayed and fought,
and she's still
staying and fighting.
SARAH:
And I think
having Natalie come back
into the game actually, like,
was a blessing for me.
PROBST:
How so?
SARAH:
Well, had the Edge not been
available this season,
there's information
I would've never got
till after the game,
and I would've continued
to play it differently
than the way
I needed to play it.
PROBST:
Natalie, what was
that information?
I told everybody, basically,
Tony's the guy
that everybody's saying
is playing the best game.
Whether or not it's true,
from my perspective
and everybody on Extinction,
Tony's running the show.
And I think
that really fired Sarah up.
SARAH:
I-It did. It made me realize
that if a woman in this game
lies or-or cheats or steals,
then she's fake
and phony and a bitch.
If a guy does it,
it's good gameplay.
they're a stud.
What it is is it's a gender
bias, and it holds me back.
It holds other women back
from playing the game the way
we should be allowed
to play the game.
And it made me realize
that I, for two years,
have been so hard on myself
from Game Changers
that I felt like
I was such a bad person,
and I'm not.
And, um...
And I can finally...
I really feel like
I can let that go now.
Like, she brought that to me.
And it's... It is such,
like, a weight
lifted off my shoulder.
I know who I am,
and I can do a lot of things,
and I'm not scared of anyone.
And I'm gonna prove it.
I ran seven marathons in
seven days on seven continents.
I've been on the SWAT team.
I've been a police officer.
I work my ass off
for everything I have
because I'm a strong woman,
and I can play however I want.
Because if a man can do it,
so can I.
And so can Michele,
and so can Denise,
and so can Natalie.
And I will not be defeated
by a gender bias.
The biggest weight
that has held me down
for two years has been lifted,
and it feels great.
Tony, we are
in a cultural shift,
and it's beautiful,
and it's powerful.
But to Sarah's point,
men have never had to deal
with a lot of the labels
that come with
playing aggressively
or lying or cheating.
So, as a man,
are you starting to reappreciate
and reevaluate
how you would label people
-even in this game?
-Um, no. I-I...
I'm not reappreciating it
or reevaluating it
'cause I already know it.
I see it in real life.
I see it at my workplace.
I see it everywhere.
We all know it.
PROBST:
Ben, how about for you?
BEN:
Um, I know that women
can do anything
that a man can do,
especially in Survivor.
And there's a lot
that goes on in Survivor
that doesn't relate outside,
and strong women like Sarah
is bringing it to light.
And I think that everybody
needs to respect women,
because they're all our mothers,
and they're our daughters.
And that's what we got
-to sit back and realize.
-PROBST: Well, then,
let me own my part.
I'm certain right now,
if I were to look back
at all of the comments
I have made over 20 years,
I would find
the exact same bias in me.
Who-who I call by last names.
Guys have different
relationships with each other,
and I might not know how to have
that relationship with a woman.
So I'll definitely own the fact
that I don't think I saw it
when Survivor started.
And I don't think I even knew
I was supposed to look for it.
But I'm very much aware
of it now, and I'm grateful
that we can open up
and investigate,
even though it comes with crisis
or it comes with some hardship
or it comes with some tears.
Whatever it is,
it's out there,
and it's being talked about.
You can start calling me Lacina.
(laughter)
PROBST:
All right, Lacina.
Let's get back to the game.
Natalie, what do you do
to try to ease this weight
off your shoulder that you're
the easy target,
or there's this uncertainty
about if you came back
with an advantage,
and therefore,
that's another reason
-to get rid of you.
-NATALIE: Yeah, I mean, clearly,
it's them four strong,
Michele's on the bottom,
and I'm rock-bottom.
And if she had not won immunity
and I had won immunity,
it would be her
going home, but I'm still here
hoping that something's
gonna happen tonight
that shakes this foursome up.
PROBST:
One thing, Tony,
that never changes
in this game
is when somebody is desperate,
they will find a crack
where you think there isn't one.
And when Natalie says, "Hey, all
I have to do is go to Michele
"and say, 'You were
on the bottom, and it was you
if not me,'"
suddenly, this is a problem.
Yeah, that's not
finding a crack, Jeff.
That's creating a crack.
Again, the Edge has
all the intel from our side.
Every time somebody gets
voted off,
they tell them who has idols,
how many idols they have,
where the idols
are hiding at.
We don't know nothing.
We only know what
they tell us, and, you know,
you got to either accept it
at face value,
or you got to look
a little bit deeper into it.
And that's why there's a lot
of confusion with this twist,
because you're battling
the unknown.
It's like you're fighting
the invisible person.
It's unknown,
but at the same time,
I feel like there's a lot
of things that people are
just keeping their blinders to.
And, so,
I talked to all the ladies.
I said, "Listen,
don't shoot the messenger,
"but you guys
are giving Tony $2 million
unless you guys
shake things up."
Wow. Big-time move.
She's good
at what she does, Jeff.
PROBST:
All right.
Time to vote.
Natalie, you're up.
♪ ♪
I'll go tally the votes.
If anybody has a hidden immunity
idol and you want to play it,
now would be the time to do so.
Yeah, Jeff.
I'm playing this for myself
'cause...
I want to be here tomorrow,
-and there's no point saving it.
-Okay.
That's crazy. Just like that.
This is a hidden immunity idol.
Any votes cast for Natalie
will not count.
Yeah, I'm playing mine,
too, Jeff.
This is a hidden immunity idol.
Any votes cast for Tony
will not count.
-Okay. I'll read...
-BEN: Hey, Jeff.
Hold on a sec.
Since we're talking about
beautiful, strong women,
my wife keeps putting
these darn things in my boots.
(Ben exhales)
And I don't want to go home
with it there.
-Thank you.
-Yes, sir.
This is a hidden immunity idol.
Any votes cast for Ben
will not count.
Okay.
I'll read the votes.
First vote:
Natalie. Does not count.
Natalie.
Does not count.
Ben.
We have no votes cast
for any player.
So, we're gonna revote.
Here's how it's gonna work.
You cannot vote for Michele.
She has the immunity necklace.
You cannot vote
for Natalie, Ben or Tony
because they played idols.
The only people you can vote for
are either Denise or Sarah.
Denise and Sarah,
because you can
only vote for each other,
you won't vote.
Four people voting between
Denise and Sarah.
And let me explain
how the tiebreaker works
in this situation.
Our normal tiebreaker states
when two people are tied,
they become immune
and everybody else draws rocks.
There is nobody to draw rocks.
So, in this situation,
if there is a tie
between Denise and Sarah,
you will settle it
with a fire-making showdown.
-Those are the stakes.
-ADAM: Wow.
-Oh, wow.
-Wow.
Natalie,
if you'll come grab the urn.
♪ ♪
I'll go tally the votes.
I'll read the votes.
First vote:
Denise.
17th person voted out:
That's three. That's enough.
-Need to bring me your torch.
-It's all good.
-PROBST: Bring me your torch.
-DENISE: Love you, lady.
(both grunt)
-I'm so, so, so sorry, man.
-It's okay 'cause I got to...
No. (grunts)
-(Denise mumbles)
-BEN: Come here, Mama.
♪ ♪
Denise, the tribe has spoken.
Kick ass.
Love you, Mama D.
PROBST:
Well,
another crazy Tribal
in what has been
an absolutely
unpredictable season.
Grab your torches.
Head back to camp. Good night.
I may not have won the game,
but I get to be known
as the Queenslayer.
Nobody else did that move
with me.
I got more than I needed
and more than I wanted
out of my second time out here,
and I'm incredibly grateful
for that.
But Mama D is out.
♪ ♪
TONY:
I have the utmost respect
for you and for Sarah,
but when I ask you guys
something or tell you guys,
-"Listen, if you guys are 100%,
then I'll back down."
-Yeah.
-I always compromise.
But you guys never do
with me, man.
I was telling you guys,
"Please, let's do this.
Let's try to figure this out
so we don't waste our idols,"
-and you guys
didn't want to budge.
-Right.
-You didn't want to listen
to me, you know.
-Yeah.
-I am sorry. When we left...
-No, no, no, man.
When we left
and her ... jacket was here,
there was something up.
-You know what I mean?
-TONY: I know.
I'm so angry. I'm frustrated.
Denise goes home.
I lose an idol.
Ben loses an idol.
We're vulnerable
at the final five.
Nice job, guys.
SARAH:
Okay.
TONY:
The only good part is there was
three idols played.
At least one
is coming back into the game,
and I want to get a jump
on finding it.
I'm not gonna wait
till the sun comes out, so...
I do one of
my midnight specials.
(chuckles): I get a shell,
I throw some coal in it,
and off I go
into the jungle,
searching for the idol.
♪ ♪
So, I'm feeling around,
feeling around,
searching high and low,
everywhere in between,
and I come up short.
And then here comes the sun,
and then here comes
everybody else.
And now I'm getting nervous,
because with a little luck,
anybody can find an idol.
♪ ♪
Yeah.
NATALIE:
Oh, my God. I can't believe it.
This would be the...
probably the 50th time
I've stuck my hand
into a little crevice.
And I felt a rope, and my heart
just starts pounding so fast.
NATALIE:
This is awesome.
I have an immunity idol.
It shows dedication
and that relentlessness
on a goal is something
that I've been able to harness
from Extinction.
And now I'm gonna use it
to break up those three.
So, my work is
just getting started.
So it's got to be around
somewhere.
Yeah.
BEN:
Me and Tony have been scouring
this whole island.
There's two idol hounds
out here,
and neither of us have found it.
So, that's starting to get
a little concerning,
'cause that means
that possibly Michele
or Natalie have found it.
And if that's the case
and one of those girls
wins immunity, we're screwed.
♪ ♪
Come on in, guys!
All right.
Let's get to today's
immunity challenge.
First things first, Michele,
the second time
-in a row
I'm gonna take it back.
-Dang it.
Thanks.
Once again,
immunity is back up for grabs.
For today's challenge,
you're gonna race
through a series of obstacles,
collecting a key along the way.
That key will unlock
two sandbags.
First player
to land both their sandbags
on their target...
...wins immunity,
guaranteed a spot
in the final four, which means
you have a shot at the end,
either by winning it, by being
taken or winning in fire.
Huge stakes today.
We'll draw for spots.
We'll get started.
All right, here we go!
For immunity and a spot
in the final four.
Survivors ready?
Go!
♪ ♪
Everybody in the water.
You got to swim to your ramp.
That's stage one.
Natalie's gonna get there first.
Ben's right in it.
Here comes Michele,
Sarah and Tony.
Natalie's up the ramp.
Ben is up the ramp.
Both are in the water.
Here comes Sarah and Michele.
Sarah's in the water.
Michele in the water.
There goes Tony.
Now you got to get across
the beam any way you want.
-(Ben grunts)
-You can walk it,
crawl it, scooch it.
It does not matter.
You're untying one key
along the way.
Natalie has her key.
Ben has his key.
Sarah's in it.
Here comes Tony.
Nat's good.
Ben is good.
Sarah has her key.
Tony's working on his key.
Michele taking a long time
on that beam.
Sarah's good.
She's in the water.
Now you got to
throw yourself under the net,
crawling in the sand.
Tony's in the water.
Michele in last,
working on her key.
Ben takes the lead now.
He's through first.
Here comes Natalie.
Sarah's in the net.
Tony right behind.
Michele still on the beam.
Oh, God. I'm so scared.
PROBST:
Ben has his two sandbags free.
He can start tossing.
Got to land both of them.
Ben close with the first.
On and off with the second.
Ben zoned in very quickly.
Natalie on and off.
Sarah unlocking her sandbags.
Tony unlocking his sandbags.
Michele's in the water now.
You've got to get both bags
on the target.
If you knock one off,
you got to land it again.
Tony now in on it.
Sarah's in on it.
Guaranteed spot at four.
Anything can happen at four.
Here comes Michele,
still digging to stay in this.
Tony on and off.
Ben has his first bag!
He's got one left.
Everybody chasing Ben now.
Sarah short.
Trying to dial in that touch.
Ben for the win.
Oh! On and off.
Stayed for a second
but rolled off.
Tony's on.
He's got his first sandbag.
It's Tony and Ben now.
-(grunts)
-Ben on and off again.
Tony can win it now right here.
Tony on and off.
-Ben on and off again!
-(grunts)
Wow.
Ben and Tony are all around it.
They're hitting
their target time after time,
but you got to get it to stick.
And Tony does!
Tony wins individual immunity.
Guaranteed a spot
in the final four.
Wow.
BEN:
The good thing is
is that Tony won immunity.
However, neither of us have
been able to find the idol.
So the risk is we do not know
what Natalie has.
If we all put our votes
on Natalie right now
and then she pulls out an idol,
that's unnerving.
♪ ♪
-Good job, Tony.
-Yeah.
-Good job, brother.
-Oh, thank you, man.
-Good job, man.
-Hey, thanks.
NATALIE:
Even though
Tony won the necklace,
I still want to break up
this three.
And the only one of them
that might flip is Sarah.
Sarah?
Same.
NATALIE:
I do have an idol,
but self-preservation
only gets me till tomorrow.
And if we don't break up
this threesome today,
it's not happening.
SARAH:
Who?
TONY:
Natalie and Michele.
Natalie-- she's not
looking for an idol.
They might have found it, Sarah.
So this is what we have--
Just to make sure,
I have to go in my spy nest.
-All right.
-So I need you
to try to get the girls.
-SARAH: Okay.
-Or we can say,
"Girls, let's talk."
-And then I want to hear
what they say.
-And see what they say.
-Yeah.
-Okay. All right.
I'm gonna go
in the spy nest now.
-Okay.
-I-I don't think they have it,
-but just in case. All right?
-All right.
♪ ♪
SARAH:
All right, what are
you thinking, girl?
NATALIE:
Well, if I was Tony--
I'm trying to put myself
in his shoes.
Obviously, I don't know
if he wants to be like,
"All right, Michele or Natalie,"
or if he wants to do
something bigger
and get rid of,
I don't know, Ben.
But obviously,
you three are like,
"I'm not gonna write
each other's names down."
(chuckles):
So...
Well, and that's just it.
That's what I have to debate is:
-How can I win this game?
-Yeah.
I think last Tribal was
probably your best Tribal.
-SARAH: Yeah, but it doesn't
win you the game.
-No,
but when you have moments
like that, people do give a ....
It's not fake.
Are-are you only willing
to write down Ben's name?
I would rather write Ben's
because I would rather not
-compete against Ben
in fire, ever.
-Sure.
So this is my situation, right?
So if it's three of us
and Ben goes home tonight,
I feel like you have an idol,
so I'm not, I'm not
pitching anything...
SARAH:
What is that? What do you have?
Something to keep me safe.
Let me see.
Shut up.
NATALIE:
Yeah. I found it.
Where'd you find it?
Um, on the way to water,
around that back way.
TONY:
So I climb up the tree,
listening to their
conversation, and then
my eyes are like "bing!"
And sure enough,
Natalie tells Sarah
she has an idol.
SARAH:
All right.
So what do we want to do?
NATALIE:
So, Michele,
day one, she told me,
"I'm a hundred percent
with you,
and we both want
to work with you."
SARAH:
The three of us need
to come to a consensus.
-Yeah.
-All right.
Let's get back,
check on that rice.
-Um...
-Between you four,
who do you think
would've had the best chance of
winning immunity-- I mean...
(conversation fades)
(quietly): That was
the worst experience of my life.
They were talking
for, like, an hour.
Look at me.
My legs are shaking.
I almost died.
But after she showed her
the idol,
I knew that we're all good.
I saw it and heard it all.
How spot-on am I
with these girls?
-Super spot-on. So...
-I knew it, man.
Okay, so here's what I think
we need to do.
I don't think she'd play it
for Michele.
-I think she'll play it
for herself.
-Yeah.
-So the votes need
to go on Michele.
-Yeah.
-Right? 'Cause we don't
want Ben out, right?
-Yeah. Yeah.
You're gonna tell them
that the plan is
for me and Ben to vote Natalie,
so then she thinks
the votes are gonna go on her.
You know what I mean?
Knowing that Natalie
has an idol,
we're all voting for Michele.
We can't let her
stay here any longer.
She's just gonna cause
trouble and chaos,
so she's going home tonight.
Done.
But I put my idol in my buff.
-Mm-hmm.
-I'm standing,
and she's like, "What's that?"
I was like,
"Okay, it's-it's the idol."
-MICHELE: Damn it.
-But it ended up working--
No, but it ended up working
'cause then she was like,
"Wow. All right, yeah."
Natalie...
she's gonna vote me out tonight.
-No.
-Yes.
They know that I have nothing,
and they are going to go
at this point with a safe bet.
MICHELE:
What an absolute disaster.
Sarah knows now
that Natalie has an idol
and I have nothing.
And since I don't see those
three cracking on each other,
I am the obvious target
tonight.
SARAH:
They're scheming now.
BEN:
Yeah.
Here's the problem.
Do you think she would
play her idol for Michele?
BEN:
Coming from the edge, probably.
I mean, that's the kind of move
she's gonna have to make
to win it.
Plays an idol for herself
one Tribal.
Plays an idol for someone else
the next Tribal.
I mean, I'm all for
writing down Michele, but...
-And they play-- I know.
-It's okay.
Listen, I've accepted my fate
in this game.
I'm okay with it.
I won't be mad at you.
I won't be mad at Tony.
SARAH:
Well, I'm not writing
your name down.
Listen, just hear me out.
If you want to put my name down,
use that as your résumé
and win it, I'm for it.
Ben.
No, I'm serious, though.
Because, listen... (stammers)
you gave such a good speech
last night...
SARAH:
You're seriously
okay with that?
BEN:
Mm-hmm.
SARAH:
Ben.
Listen, that way, you can't say
you got drug along.
-Ben.
-You know what I'm saying?
Are you being serious?
I'm being whatever this is.
I love you.
Ben.
You have my permission.
..., Ben.
Why are you doing this?
You have to go
... win it though. Okay?
BEN:
I've struggled enough
in my heart.
I know she's been
struggling to protect me,
and I don't want
to drag her down.
It's just, I feel in my heart
the right thing to do
is to give her permission.
And she doesn't have to, but
if she does, she does, you know?
I know, no matter what happens,
I'm gonna walk away from
Survivor with my head held high
and actually have
actual friends.
'Cause having friends
is worth more than money.
SARAH:
Ben has given me the blessing
to vote him out.
And it tears me up, like...
He's looked out for me
this whole game,
and I've looked out for him.
And in a game where
you can't trust anyone,
we trust each other 100%.
And to see him in tears
destroys me.
He's the last person
that I want to hurt.
MICHELE:
I think she's
straight-up lying.
-I-I'm 95% confident that
they're gonna go on me tonight.
-Yeah.
SARAH:
But in order for me
to even have a shot,
I have to make a move.
And I have to make a move
without Tony.
I've had to make hard decisions,
but this one's the worst ever.
And I don't know
what I'm gonna do.
♪ ♪
PROBST:
So I was thinking about
you guys today,
and I have a thought.
This season was envisioned
as a celebration.
Let's bring back
20 of the greatest
and let's just watch them play,
one more time.
But when you invite winners back
and you call it Winners at War,
you also invite
that competitive spirit
that got all you guys here
to win the game
in the first place.
And you started at this pace
that has been unforgiving,
like a group of marathon runners
that went a little too quick
that first mile and they are
trying desperately to finish.
Painful to go through,
powerful to watch.
And one of the themes
this season
has been breakthroughs.
Sarah, you had one at the last
Tribal that was amazing.
Been carrying around two years
of pain that you now realize
wasn't even yours to carry;
it was some gender bias crap.
-It's now gone.
-It's Lacina.
You're right.
(laughter)
Lacina.
So here's the thought.
Is it possible that Survivor
serves the purpose of
a well-intentioned
but relentless adversary
that pushes you
to deal with stuff?
It's not just 39 days in Fiji.
That's a great vacation.
This is 39 days of
intense personal scrutiny.
SARAH:
Yeah. It brings out
the best in you
and it brings out
the worst in you.
I always chose to ignore when it
would bring out the best in me,
and I wouldn't give myself
credit for that,
and I would downplay
those moments.
And I would take when
it brings out the worst in me
and inflate it.
I was so hard on myself,
but I think you have to
forgive yourself, and it's okay.
But I think everybody
walks away from this growing.
And so if that's what
I get out of this journey,
it's worth everything for me.
PROBST:
Ben, when Sarah said
she downplays the good
but really highlights the bad,
you were nodding.
What were you relating to
about that?
Coming out this time, I-I didn't
want to be that person again.
She talks about growth,
and that's what this season
was for me.
It was growth.
I wanted to be
a more positive person,
you know, represent my family
in-in a better light,
and walk away from
this experience with friends,
not go back home and not like
the person that I was, you know?
And I think that is worth more
than any, um, dollar sign
or anything like that.
That's been my goal.
So what is it, Tony, that, in
this game, highlights the bad
in your eyes, when the audience
so often sees the good?
'Cause they're not
dealing with the people.
Th-They're watching a show for
entertainment purposes only.
They're not dealing with
the emotions and the feelings
that you get from people
that you bond with.
They don't see
the social part of it.
They see the strategic part.
"I'm gonna blindside
this person.
I'm gonna play an idol
and send somebody home."
And then I'm here with people
that I just know,
and it's like
the closer I get to them,
the harder it is
to vote them off.
So that's the feeling
that nobody can get
from watching it on TV.
PROBST:
So, Lacina,
when you get back to camp,
Tony's got his fourth win,
there's only four other people,
what happens?
What's that like?
SARAH:
Well, I think
it's time to evaluate:
How do you get through tonight
and set yourself up
for success tomorrow?
So I think
everybody had conversations
with everyone today,
because the game turned
not so alliance based and turned
more into
an individual game today.
This is the last time
we write someone's name down
to vote them out.
After this, everybody's on their
own to save their own butt.
Ben, was it different
for you today?
It was a little different.
And tonight is about being brave
and being strong
and having friendships
and just staying positive, Jeff.
That's all we got to do.
PROBST:
So, Michele, it sounds like
without anybody saying it,
the collective unconscious
all just sort of happened, which
is, "Oh, we're on our own now."
MICHELE:
I don't know.
I have been running against
this wall of an alliance
for over a week now...
You're talking with
Sarah, Ben and Tony?
MICHELE:
Yeah, that's right.
I think these players found
a very strong alliance,
very early on, that carried them
through this game.
I've been in
a very different position,
so of course my optimism says,
"I hope I can work my way in,"
but my realistic side
of me says,
"I haven't been able to do that
yet, so curb your expectation."
All right, it is time to vote.
Michele, you're up.
♪ ♪
I'll go tally the votes.
If anybody has
a hidden immunity idol
and you want to play it,
now would be the time to do so.
-Okay.
-Oh.
♪ ♪
I hope this goes as planned.
-I'm playing this
for myself tonight.
-Okay.
This is a hidden immunity idol.
Any votes cast for Natalie
will not count.
Wow.
I'll read the votes.
First vote:
Ben.
Michele.
Two votes Ben, one vote Michele.
Michele. We're tied.
Two votes Ben,
two votes Michele,
one vote left.
18th person voted out of
Survivor: Winners at War...
-...Ben.
-Ooh.
Love you.
-Hope you all are
ready to party.
-(laughter)
You know I'm getting a hug
from you, too, Mr. Jeff.
I'll take it.
Ben, the tribe has spoken.
Thanks for playing.
Yeah, buddy.
Aha!
PROBST:
You've made it
to the final four.
Tomorrow you will compete in
your final immunity challenge.
Get some rest.
Grab your torches,
head back to camp.
Good night.
BEN:
This has been a humbling
and a fantastic
learning experience for myself.
I got what I needed
out of this season:
a lot of self-growth.
I left it all out there.
I'm proud of my game and
grateful for the experience
that Survivor has given me
and my children and my wife.
Very much appreciative
and-and blessed.
♪ ♪
Come on in, guys!
(sighs)
All right.
Shall we get to
your final immunity challenge?
First things first, Tony,
for the fourth time,
got to take back the necklace.
-Thank you.
-Yep.
For the last time,
immunity is back up for grabs.
For today's challenge,
you'll have one hand
tied behind your back.
On my go, you'll drop a ball
down a chute.
It will spiral to the bottom.
You'll catch it,
put it back in.
At regular intervals,
we will add more balls,
making it more difficult.
If at any point a ball drops,
you're out.
Last person left standing wins
immunity, is guaranteed a spot
at the final Tribal Council
where you will get a chance
to plead your case to the jury
about why you deserve
the title of Sole Survivor
and the $2 million prize
that comes with it.
In addition, you control
the fate of the other three.
Who do you bring with you?
Who do you force to make fire?
The biggest challenge of
Survivor: Winners at War
is here.
Let's do it.
All right.
Here we go.
You'll have five seconds
to drop your first ball.
Everybody, grab one.
Five, four, three,
two, one.
And it's on.
The final immunity challenge
in our 40th season of Survivor.
Natalie, Michele,
Tony and Sarah.
Your ball will rotate
which side it comes out
automatically every time.
So if it comes out on
the right side, the next time,
it will be on the left.
This'll continue
as we add more balls into this.
Couple of
interesting statistics.
Of the four of you,
all of whom won the game,
only one of you won
the final immunity challenge
in their season: Michele.
Contrast that
against this statistic.
We have done this challenge
three times
as the final immunity challenge,
and every person who won it
won the game.
All right,
you each have 15 seconds
to place another ball.
That's a big window.
You can use that time
however you want.
You got to stay focused
right now.
This is that moment right here.
Everybody now has two balls
in motion.
Now it just got
a little more difficult.
Now you have one ball
coming out on the right,
the next ball on the left.
That ball drops,
you're out and you are not
in control of your fate tonight.
♪ ♪
All right,
everybody has 15 seconds
to place a third ball.
Natalie drops.
Tony drops his.
Michele drops hers.
Sarah drops hers.
Everybody now with three balls
in motion.
Now the challenge is full-on.
You got to be
on your toes now.
Always thinking,
"Right, left, right, left."
-(shouts)
-Tony drops.
He's first out.
No shot at immunity.
It is Natalie,
Michele and Sarah.
Three women now
fighting for immunity.
This game requires so much.
It is an all-encompassing
challenge of the human spirit,
depriving you of
all of your basic needs,
all while everybody else in the
game is trying to take you out.
All right,
you each have 15 seconds
to place another ball.
Natalie drops.
Michele drops hers.
-Sarah drops. She's out.
-(grunts)
We're down to two.
They are side by side.
It is Natalie and Michele,
both with four balls.
One of them is guaranteed a spot
at the final Tribal Council.
Five balls is the most we have
ever done in this challenge.
You are at four.
Cannot lose your concentration.
Both women zoned in.
Michele very steady.
Nice save by Natalie.
All right,
you each have 15 seconds
to place your fifth ball.
We're live
during this transition.
Ten seconds left.
Michele drops hers.
Natalie drops.
Both women have all five balls
in motion now.
The most we've ever done
in this challenge.
The pace is very fast now.
One mistake and it's over.
Nice save by Natalie.
Pacing of your balls
is so critical right now,
how fast they kick out
of that chute.
Natalie again
with a nice bobble and save.
Michele with a really nice pace.
Natalie with another save.
Never has to be pretty
on Survivor.
-(shouts)
-Oh, my God!
-Michele drops!
-Did I win?! (shouts)
-It's over!
-Natalie has won
individual immunity...
-Oh, my God!
-Oh, my God.
-...and has come
all the way back
from being voted out on day two
and is back now
at the final Tribal Council.
-Wow.
-(Natalie pants)
(sputters)
Natalie, come on over.
Jeff, this doesn't
seem real right now.
It's real.
Individual immunity is yours.
You are guaranteed
a spot at the final three.
-(Natalie exclaims)
-You're in charge
of what happens
for the rest of the night
as well.
You're gonna take one person
and sit them next to you
and force two people
to make fire.
All right, grab your stuff,
head back to camp.
-See you tonight
at Tribal Council.
-Thanks, Jeff.
Congrats.
TONY:
Today was the biggest
immunity challenge
of the season.
I could've tied a record,
which is five
immunity challenge wins.
All I do is catch the ball,
put it back,
catch the ball, put it back,
and I would've been
in good shape.
I lost focus for a second,
and just like that,
my game is in the fate of fire.
♪ ♪
NATALIE:
I'm so excited.
I'm proud of myself
that I never stopped trying
to give it my best shot.
TONY:
Oh, so this is the knife, huh?
-SARAH: Yes.
-NATALIE:
But before the sun sets,
I have the biggest decision
of my life.
Yeah, absolutely.
-Against each other.
-I know.
TONY:
So I'm pretty certain that
Natalie's gonna throw Sarah
under the bus
and make me go against
the other cop.
Damn, Sarah,
that's how our story ends?
-Cops-R-Us, man?
We-we kill each other?
-No, it's not. It's not.
W-We don't know that yet.
What is the other strategy?
This?
I don't like that way.
TONY:
That's how you do it.
-SARAH: Why?
-Y-You're hitting it
too straight on.
Straighten up the knife
a little bit. Yeah, like that.
-This way?
-Yeah, not that much,
but you know.
You're breaking the flint,
Sarah.
You got to be careful.
Right?
That is right.
I'm not even gonna practice
if you go up against me.
'Cause you suck.
Now, how do we get you up?
How did you do that?
I'm gonna have a hard time, man.
MICHELE:
You go, girl.
Not bad.
NATALIE:
Tony's the biggest threat
in the game,
and getting him out
would be ideal.
So there's two options:
Michele and Sarah.
The reason I wouldn't want
Sarah beating Tony
is that gives her this really
strong story at the end.
So option one then is
Michele and Tony go to fire.
For me, my goal is to be able
to make Tony look
as less desirable as a winner
as possible.
Obviously, you don't want
to go to fire,
but if Sarah wins,
that gives her cred
to beat me in the end.
MICHELE:
I would love
to win the fire-making
challenge.
It's a really good endcap.
It's just a really risky way
to end the game.
But it's times like this
when, honestly,
my strengths have come out.
TONY:
So I was watching Michele.
She's striking it.
She's like...
(imitates clicking) Flame.
So I'm a little concerned
about that.
Doing it quicker than that?
-Yeah.
-How are you doing it?
I'm not telling you,
just in case we go up together.
Good job, Mich.
-How's Michele doing up there?
-She's doing good.
-Oh, she is?
-Yeah.
-She making fire?
-She is?
-Yeah.
TONY:
I literally sat there
and watched Michele
scrape it once or twice,
the magnesium, and she was good.
-Damn, I need to get good
at this, man.
-I know, T.
SARAH: We're just grinding
all afternoon,
because you have no choice
but to grind at this point.
I hope she picks me.
I want to step up to the plate.
I'm not scared. Pick me.
Wow. Now I'm panicking, man.
SARAH:
Tony's not in
the right headspace
to make fire.
Maybe he can get there,
but if he doesn't get there,
I'm gonna beat him in fire.
TONY:
I wish I could have
the easy route,
but I always take
the hard route.
(sighs):
Ah, man.
That's what I do, man.
I grind.
I work hard,
I'm gonna practice hard,
I'm gonna try to perform hard.
Tonight's gonna be
put up or shut up.
Fire!
I'm either gonna win this game
or I'm gonna lose trying.
It all boils down to this.
♪ ♪
NATALIE:
Tonight, I'm sitting
in the front seat,
after being in the back seat
all this time,
getting voted off first.
I would rather be
in this position
than having
somebody else dictate
what's gonna happen
with my fate on the game.
I have all the power
and the biggest and last
decision of the game.
Now bring in the members
of our jury.
All right, so let's get into it.
Sophie is not with us tonight.
Sophie's not feeling well,
so she can't attend
tonight's Tribal,
-but you guys will
fill her in...
-Yeah, for sure.
...in as unbiased a way
as possible.
-Of course.
-All right.
Natalie, the final immunity
challenge, you pull it out.
Go back to that moment,
when you think about day two,
you're the first person sent
to the Edge of Extinction,
all alone,
to this moment, where you are
in the final three,
one of the most
improbable things
that you could ever imagine
on Survivor.
NATALIE:
It's crazy.
Felt like a dream, but I think
it was the only thing
that kept me going at Extinction
was telling myself
that I would get this shot
to battle back,
and then you putting
this necklace on me was
the most amazing feeling
I've had so far.
Hard work pays off.
So, Michele, what was
the afternoon like?
I'm guessing everybody wanted
a chance to talk to Natalie.
Well, Natalie actually
came back to camp
and said that she should
allow us to converse
and she wanted some time alone
to contemplate her decision.
And since then, I didn't eat,
I didn't take a sip of my water.
I practiced fire
from the moment that I got back.
PROBST:
Tony, do you spend much time
thinking about who you want
to go up against
or do you spend
more time thinking,
"I just need to be the best,
that's it"?
I just come here and give it
my best. That's all I do.
I play as hard as I can,
uh, nonstop,
hoping that my best is
good enough to win in the end.
So you don't care
who you go up against in fire?
-Right now? No.
-How about you, Sarah?
Do you have a preference?
SARAH:
If I'm making fire,
it's gonna be against Tony.
And I don't think
I would truly want to make fire
against anyone else.
Why?
(voice breaking):
I mean, I love this guy and...
Oh. Stop, stop, man.
-Relax.
-He's my partner.
And, uh...
if we're gonna get shot,
I'd rather us shoot each other
than have someone else
shoot at us, so...
Wait, you want to shoot me now?
-Yeah.
-(Tony chuckles)
PROBST:
How about you, Michele?
Is there a preference?
If I had to make fire, I would
want to make it against Tony,
because I think that he stands
the best shot of
winning this game right now.
And, Natalie,
that's the dilemma you have is:
Do you put yourself in that spot
and say, "I'm gonna just do it,"
or, "Whose the best person
to try to get rid of
who I think might be
my biggest target?"
NATALIE:
Exactly.
And I would love to battle Tony,
send him home
and sit here tomorrow...
Well, what's stopping you?
Um, be-- I have to be
brutally honest with myself
and ask myself, "Do I feel
100% confidence in beating him?"
At this point, I feel like,
when I won the challenge today
and you put this immunity
necklace around my neck,
I knew that I had done enough
and felt satisfied
to leave the fire-making
to somebody else tonight.
PROBST:
All right, so let's get to it,
Natalie.
You have one decision to make.
Who are you going to bring
with you to the end?
And the two you leave behind
will move right over here
and showdown in fire.
The person I'm bringing
with me tonight
is gonna be Michele.
She's gonna be sitting
at the final three with me.
-Surprise, surprise.
-Like I said,
until last minute, it wasn't.
But I want to see
the end of this alliance.
I think that Michele and I
worked the last couple of days
really hard.
-And we took apart
the foursome...
-(coughing)
-...one by one.
-Sorry.
-And this'll be
the last showdown.
-(Sarah coughing)
And I'm hoping that this girl
is sitting with me at the end.
PROBST:
So let's set the stage.
Natalie, you're in
the final three.
-Yeah.
-You are bringing
Michele with you.
You are going to force
Sarah and Tony
to battle it out for that final
spot in a fire-making showdown.
Tony, you'll take
this spot in red.
Sarah will take blue.
♪ ♪
-All right, Tony, Sarah,
are you ready?
-Yeah.
Good luck.
This could be a $2 million fire.
Finally gonna have to say
I'm better than you.
Yeah, it's all right.
Here we go. Begin.
You both have the same supplies.
What you do with them
is what matters.
Out of the gate,
two different approaches.
Tony scraping magnesium.
Sarah building a little nest.
PROBST:
Tony going for a spark.
A little flame.
Got to get it to take.
He's got magnesium in that husk.
Trying to get it to catch.
Sarah now scraping magnesium.
Sarah has a little bit of flame.
It goes out.
Tony has a little bit of flame.
Can he keep it going?
(blowing)
Key is, once you get it,
to nurture it
so it doesn't go out.
Tony's trying to keep his going.
Blowing ever so gently.
Sarah not panicking.
Sarah has another baby flame.
Yep. Yep. Yep.
Sarah's flame is going now.
Tony's is going.
Sarah's trying
to keep hers going.
Oh, my God.
PROBST: Both very close with
about the same amount of flame.
Now it's gonna come down to
who can build a fire
high enough
to burn through that rope.
Both doing a nice job.
You only have so much husk,
which is why it's so critical
when you use it.
Sarah's flame is now
in the lead.
Sarah's using
all of her coconut husk.
Oh. Oh.
PROBST:
Trying to burn
through that rope.
Oh, ....
PROBST: Tony's flame
starting to diminish.
Now Sarah's is back
diminishing again.
Add some sticks.
PROBST: Tony building
a giant structure for a bonfire.
(quiet murmuring)
All that matters is
burning through that rope,
and now it's Tony
back in the lead.
This has been back and forth,
-one of the best fire-making
challenges we have ever had.
-(others murmuring)
PROBST:
Sarah's flame is back now.
Wow.
PROBST:
Tony's flame is burning strong.
It's starting to burn
through that rope now.
PROBST: Sarah's flame
burning very strong,
starting to burn
through that rope.
Tony's flame is
really strong right now.
It is a showdown.
-Yeah!
-(whooping)
-PROBST: And it is over.
Tony defeats Sarah.
He'll take the third
and final spot
at the final Tribal Council.
What a showdown
between competitors.
Cops-R-Us.
SARAH:
Oh, my God, you won.
I love you.
Hey. Hey.
Hey. We did-- Hey.
-You don't have to be sorry
for anything.
-Sorry.
-Hey, listen.
-I got you. I know.
I want you to enjoy
that breakfast tomorrow.
-All right?
-Yeah.
Hey. Hey.
Enjoy this.
-You got one more day
and you're done.
-Shh. Shh.
One more.
TONY:
I'm so sorry, man.
SARAH:
Don't apologize to me.
I'm not going
to say sorry for it.
-I love you.
Thanks.
PROBST:
So, Sarah, how does
that feel right now
knowing that the quest
for the two million
and the title is over,
by a few sticks?
SARAH:
(sighs) Um...
(clears throat)
I mean, it's...
it's okay.
And when you hear
people say that,
it doesn't mean
they're giving up.
It means that...
they got something valuable
out of this experience.
And (sniffles) if I was
gonna go out of this game,
that's how I wanted to go out.
And if I wanted someone
to take me out,
that's who I wanted
to take me out.
And if someone was
gonna take him out,
I wanted it to be me.
And, um...
Tony is more than deserving to
be sitting in the final three,
and... I wish I could
be there with him.
You know?
We talked about this
for the last 38 days.
Um, it's not gonna happen,
but it's okay.
And he can still finish
what he set out to accomplish,
and I know he's gonna do it,
and so I'm fine.
PROBST:
All right, Sarah,
this season is over for you.
Need to bring me your torch.
♪ ♪
Lacina, the tribe has spoken.
-Time for you to go.
-Thanks.
It was a pleasure.
Tony...
-(sniffles)
-I love you.
Crush it tomorrow, all right?
Eat some food for me.
I'll be eating it
for you tonight.
(howls)
(sniffles)
PROBST:
Okay.
Natalie, Tony, Michele.
You had three different journeys
to get here, but you did it.
You made it to the final three
of our 40th season.
Tomorrow night,
you will face the jury,
people you voted out
of this game,
people who understand what
it takes to get to this spot.
They're gonna have
a lot of questions.
Tomorrow, somebody,
one of the three of you,
is gonna show up and seize
the title of Sole Survivor
and the $2 million prize.
One last night of sleep in Fiji.
Try to make it a good one.
See you tomorrow.
Grab your torches,
head back to camp.
Good night.
Tony's my partner in crime
for life.
If I'm gonna have to end
my Survivor career,
how else would I want to end it
than like this?
I'm emotional right now,
but because I'm happy.
I'm happy of the way
that I played.
I'm happy of the experiences
that Survivor's given me,
the friendships
they've given me.
I don't have any regrets,
and I wouldn't have wanted it
any other way.
♪ ♪
(howls)
(both howl)
NATALIE:
You got some news for us?
-You got something!
We can see it!
-What's in there?
-Ah!
-(squeals) Yes!
All right, guys.
You ready for this?
-Yes.
-All right, here we go.
"Congratulations!
"You have made it
to the final three.
-(whoops)
-"Follow the trail
"behind your camp
for your well-earned
Day 39 Survivor breakfast."
Yes! We made it!
-Food. Let's go.
-Congratulations, guys, man.
-Dirty Jersey!
-Congratulations.
-Yay.
MICHELE:
My last season,
I achieved
the ultimate accomplishment
by winning Survivor.
-(whoops)
-Absolutely. (whoops)
-Let's go!
MICHELE:
But I got so much feedback from
the public
and from my fellow contestants
that maybe I wasn't
the most deserving person.
It took something that was
my biggest accomplishment
and made it into
one of my toughest moments
in my life.
-I don't even know
where to start.
-Yay!
-TONY: Is that champagne?
-MICHELE: Mm-hmm.
But, every single day out here,
I proved
to myself that I think I am
one of the very, very best
in this game.
-Ooh! What?
-(yelps)
MICHELE:
I've been on the bottom,
constantly having
to fight my way out of it.
And now, here I am again,
in the final three,
and I feel like
this has closed a wound
that has been open for me
for a while.
And I will go in tonight
and make sure that I do
my darnedest to win.
May the best man or woman win.
-Congratulations, guys. Cheers.
-Cheers.
NATALIE:
Even though I have
a very nontraditional path
to the final three,
I took the hand I was dealt
and said, "You know what?
"I'm gonna play the best damn
Extinction game I can."
Bacon! Oh, my God.
Okay, so I'm gonna do
a fried egg. I can't wait.
I knew that I had the grit,
that I had the strength
and the willpower
to do what it takes.
I never gave up,
and I was relentless
in my effort to come back
into the game.
Oh, look at that.
Look at-- Oh!
NATALIE:
The most important thing I have
to get across to the jury
is to prove to the people
that don't believe in me
I was able to duke it out
with the best of the best
and I came out on top.
So I'm going to be confident,
be proud, and prove
that I deserve this $2 million.
-TONY: Are you guys excited
for tonight?
-NATALIE/MICHELE: Yeah.
-What a journey, huh?
TONY: This is an opportunity
to win a second time and prove
that I'm one of the greatest
players to ever play this game.
Everybody has
their own specialty
and what they're focused on--
they're good at challenges,
they're good at the social game,
they're good
at the strategic game.
But, me,
I do a little of everything.
And that's what it takes
to be a great player.
You have to be good at
everything Survivor has
to throw your way.
Last day on Survivor Island.
You got to just
take it all in, right?
These are all winners.
These are the best of the best.
And these jurors--
I had a big part
of ruining their chances
of winning $2 million
to better their families.
So I know the pain
that they're feeling.
The wounds are deep,
and I know they're real.
So this is gonna be
the hardest task of all,
to try to convince them
that I deserve
the title of Sole Survivor.
But I'm pretty confident
in how I played my game.
So, we always had
a queen of Survivor
for many, many years,
which was Sandra.
We never had
a king of Survivor.
Now I'm hoping that I can
take it home and be the king.
(thunder rumbling)
♪ ♪
PROBST:
All right.
Natalie, Tony, Michele,
let's get to your final
Tribal Council.
It is only fitting that this war
would come to an end
under a torrential downpour.
You guys have had a lot
to deal with this year:
20 winners; the introduction
of a fire token,
which birthed
a Survivor economy,
complete with a supply
and demand of advantages;
and Edge of Extinction,
which is playing out tonight.
Natalie earned her way
back into this game.
Your final battle
is against each other,
and it is to persuade this jury
that you are the most deserving
of the title of Sole Survivor
and the record-setting
$2 million prize
that comes with it.
All right, let's get started
with the outwit portion
of the game.
This is the social part
of the game--
the alliances, relationships.
You guys have talked a lot
about previous friendships,
how that might have factored in,
morality and ethics,
if that was important to you.
Who wants to get us going?
YUL:
All right.
Getting a little stage fright,
Jeff, but here goes.
Wait a minute.
-(others chuckling)
-You've been on Survivor twice,
-and you have stage fright?
-I mean,
you know, I'm just feeling,
kind of, pressure, but...
-Go for it, Yul. Do it, Yul.
-All right, good.
All right, ready?
-PARVATI: You can do it, Yul.
-YUL: Can we go? All right.
-Yul, get us started.
-(Danni laughs)
-Cool. All right. Before
we jump in with questions,
I just really want
to offer you huge kudos
and congratulate you guys
for playing a-a great game
and getting to the end.
I mean, all of you took
a completely unique path,
encountering
different obstacles.
So, tonight,
what we really need is
for you to fill in
the missing blanks
so that we have a coherent
narrative of how you outwitted
all of us to be sitting
where you are right now.
And, on behalf of all of us,
I wish you the best of luck.
So much for stage fright.
-(laughter)
-Right.
DENISE:
Jeff, I'll start.
All right. Denise.
DENISE:
What I'm curious to know is:
What areas would you identify as
missteps or missed opportunities
related to the social aspect
that you need
to play in the game?
-Natalie.
-NATALIE: Okay.
I think my misstep
was definitely my day one.
I think I relied on my outplay
and my strength
for people to see me
as an asset to their tribe,
and I did not go to people
and say,
"Hey, like, I want
to kind of get to know you."
And it was a missed opportunity
on my part,
not reaching out more
that day one.
And that obviously led me
to getting voted off.
-How 'bout you, Michele?
-MICHELE: Well, I had
a lot of really great
one-on-one alliances.
I found the people
who kept me safe
and kept my name
out of the votes
and people
who I really relied on.
And that's great.
But if you don't have
something bigger than that,
you're just two people.
And that's why I always felt
like I was
kind of on the bottom,
because this is a numbers game
and I needed numbers.
Also, some of
my preexisting relationships
put a target on my back.
Yes, I had a relationship
with Wendell, but,
when you get on the beach, you
never know what's gonna stick
and what's not and how
that's actually gonna play out.
I don't think any of us can say
that this game went
as we expected.
-PROBST: Tony.
-TONY: Uh, y-you know what?
My first season, I wasn't as
open and vulnerable to people.
Um, soon as I hit the beach,
I was strategy and strategy.
But the missed opportunities
this season, I don't think
I had any. I think I talked
to every single one of you guys.
I-I was vulnerable to you guys.
I opened up
to every single one of youse.
And that's what determined
which way I was gonna go
into the game,
by knowing you guys
from the inside out.
NICK:
Is that okay,
to just do whatever
you got to do to build a bond,
just so that we won't
write your name down, and then,
no matter what you have to do
to get us out,
-it's worth it?
-But-but, Nick,
I found out
you were trying to blindside me.
So the bonds you and I shared
was 100% real.
I wanted to go
to the end with you,
but you didn't want
to go with me.
-So what about me?
-Same thing with you, Jeremy.
Um, I-I live a very boring
and simple life.
I don't, I don't travel nowhere.
I don't go to fine dining.
Sports--
I don't know nothing about.
But the one thing we got
close with is family bonds.
We had a lot of
vulnerable moments together.
That's all real.
I respect you as a man.
I respect you as a fireman.
I respect you as a father.
Can I say something?
I'm standing up for Jeremy
to say that Tony's response
to Jeremy, I think,
is completely false.
Don't say I didn't care. Don't
say about caring, all right?
'Cause me and him shared a lot
of intimate moments together,
and that was real.
As far as gameplay,
I did work with you
as far as I could.
But I couldn't go
any further with you
'cause I was scared of you.
I can attest for Tony's loyalty.
I found an idol while Tony
was sitting right next to me,
and he called me out on it.
And from that day forward,
he told me that he had my back.
But you're saying you're--
you could attest to his loyalty,
but we can't.
He voted us out.
ADAM:
Um, Natalie,
on the Edge, one job is
to set yourself up to be able
to get back in the game
and to be able to maybe have
an advantage in the game
if you do get back in the game.
There's no denying
that you absolutely crushed
-that part of the Edge game.
-(chuckles)
-NATALIE: Yeah.
-All you have to do besides that
is win jury votes
and make people
want you to win this game.
NATALIE:
So, when I came to Koru,
my first line of defense
was paint Tony
as the biggest threat
and make it seem like
I was the outcast at Extinction.
It was my play to paint
the picture of Extinction
to be whatever it was.
-ROB: Natalie,
if that is the case...
-Yeah.
...and you did go back
and say that strategically,
that's really smart.
-And I understand that.
-Yeah. Okay.
But for the week leading up
-before the battle-back...
-Yeah.
...why did you
completely isolate myself,
Amber, Ethan, Yul, Wendell?
All of those people
are still here on the jury.
There were two things
that I found before
I left that week-- it was
the extortion I sent to Tony
and the advantage
I sent to Nick.
Those two things
did create a rift
in my relationship
with everybody there because
it was for the first time I was
doing something super secretive,
and it meant
such a big deal to me
that I didn't know
if I wanted to tell people.
And, also,
when I'm focused on something
like the challenge,
which I was so nervous about,
I needed to breathe
and separate.
But whatever it did,
it worked for me.
And that's the real me.
Like, I know that I am
a strong personality
and it's not
everybody's cup of tea.
But I was 100% real with you
from the start,
and I did feel like
I got to know you.
And that's something
I appreciate about you, Natalie,
is that you don't put on an act.
You were always
really honest with people,
even if it pissed them off,
even if they didn't like it,
and you were out for number one
really unapologetically.
I want to hear from Tony.
We're hearing stories
from people
that you blindsided
and voted off,
and none of them
feel burned by you.
-ROB: You weren't even targeted.
-PARVATI: Yeah.
ROB:
We're fascinated.
-We want to know:
How did you do it?
-TONY: All right.
Um... (chuckles)
My-my first season,
I built a spy shack.
The second season,
I built a spy bunker.
(laughs): This season-- Adam,
you're gonna love this, man.
-Spy nest?
-TONY: Yes, man.
I used to climb up there
and listen to who wanted
to blindside me.
I used to have a bird's-eye view
-looking down
and looking at them.
-(laughter)
And at one point,
I was up there for, like,
a half hour, and I'm holding
on a twig and-and I'm shaking.
And I almost fell
out of the spy nest.
That-That's how I knew a lot
of the things that I did know,
which helped me, and that was
strategic part of it,
and the game-- let the game
evolve as it's gonna evolve.
WENDELL:
So, Tony, you made it to the end
without seeing any votes
against you. Great job.
Um, Natalie, you did play
a great Edge game.
Michele, you're
sitting here at the end.
You played a different game
than the two of them.
Can you just speak
to the outwit in your game?
MICHELE:
Sure, yeah. So, I got left out
of a lot of votes, so I kept
having to pick myself up.
I reintegrated.
I always put a smile on my face,
and it kept the target off me
a lot of the time.
I found cracks.
I moved within those cracks.
And, you know, I think I played
a really adaptable
and flexible game.
You know, Tony had these great
alliances, and they helped him.
I didn't really have anyone
helping me at the end.
It was me, alone,
when everybody was telling me
that I was gonna be
the next to go.
So, to be on the bottom
for that long,
it's pretty amazing
that I find myself sitting here
despite all my challenges.
BEN:
Yeah. You know,
as a fellow
controversial winner,
I realize why you won
your season.
And you did a heck of a job
this year,
and you should be very proud
of what you've done.
Thank you, Ben.
All right, you guys good to move
into the outplay portion?
Yeah.
PROBST:
Who wants to get us going?
You guys had a lot
to deal with this season
in terms of twists,
the fire token,
Edge of Extinction advantages
coming into the game.
Any questions in that part
of the game for these three?
I have a question.
-Natalie.
-Yeah.
Can you please share with us
all the things
that you found, won
or sent into the game?
Okay. So, if the social part is
one of my weaker parts
of the game,
this is definitely
one of the strengths.
The first one I found was
the idol that I sold to Sandra.
The second one was
the advantage to be able
to leave Tribal Council
without voting.
-Safety without power.
And I sold it to Jeremy.
The third one was
the one I sold to Sarah.
She had to sneak onto
the opposite tribe's beach
and steal an advantage
to have the extra vote.
Four was... Oh.
I extorted Tony
for six fire tokens.
The fifth one
was the Nick advantage
where he could disadvantage
somebody else.
The other two things
that everybody else
got an option to do was
the log challenge
and the coconut challenge.
Those two were
the hardest challenges
I've ever had to do.
Nonstop grinding
for one freaking fire token.
I was exhausted
and broken after both.
For me, it was really cool
to be sitting at Tribal Council,
watching the advantages
and disadvantages I sent over,
kind of being a part of the game
without actually
physically being on the island.
It was my way of playing
Survivor out on the Edge,
hoping if I got back in,
the things that I would do
would shape
the people sitting here.
BEN:
Winning an immunity challenge
is a very important part
of the game.
The challenges is how
you are guaranteed to stay.
Tony, you won four challenges
this year,
one short of tying the record.
Michele, you won two this year.
Can you guys talk about
the will and the drive
you guys had
to pull off those necklaces?
I wanted to make sure you guys
knew that I participated
in the challenge, so I gave it
my all to win that necklace.
And when I won it, I was like,
"Wow, I could win challenges."
And that's when I went to win
the next two.
I shouldn't even have
let you get that, man.
-(Tony chuckles)
-That was mine.
I should've let you
-sit out of it.
-MICHELE: I-I will say, like,
winning those immunity
challenges at clutch times,
that gives you
maybe a day in this game.
But a day changes everything.
Things shift so fast that I knew
that if I could hold out
one more day
that that could change
everything, and it did.
Things changed majorly
in my game
because of my immunity wins.
ROB:
I have a question for Natalie.
When it got down to four...
-Yeah.
-...and the fire-making
challenge was upon you,
you had a critical decision
to make.
You want to take out Tony
because everybody
on the Edge said they thought
Tony was playing the best game.
And you had that opportunity
to do it right there
and step up.
How come you didn't face him
right there in the moment?
When I won
that immunity necklace,
I felt, like, complete
in that moment.
But I knew, at the same time,
that sitting next to Tony was
the least optimal position
I want to be in tonight.
But, also, part of me
wanted to see this alliance
of four turn to three
turn to two.
Basically, I wanted to finish
them off, the whole alliance,
with them going at it at fire.
At the end of the day,
I was able to completely
pull apart the alliance.
It was what I chose to do,
and I'm at peace
with my decision that night.
ETHAN:
Tony, Michele,
uh, like, what are
your general thoughts
on the twist, the Edge?
How do you feel
that factored into your game?
(chuckles):
The Edge, it's awesome
for the people that were getting
advantages a-and tokens.
But the only thing
that came from the Edge for me
was a disadvantage.
When I first read that thing,
I was so excited. I was like,
"I get to extort somebody."
I was so happy,
and then it says,
"This is being played against
you," and I started crying.
-(laughter)
-It was, like, instant.
I had two things.
I had a disadvantage,
and I had Natalie coming back,
saying, "Hey, guys,
"you got to get rid of Tony,
'cause everybody say
he's gonna win."
And I was like,
"Guys, please
don't listen to her.
-Please don't listen.
She's lying."
-NATALIE: Well, we had...
-TONY: "She's lying.
She wants to break us."
-(chuckles)
-NATALIE: We had the...
-So, that-that's the two things
that I had going for me
for the Edge.
MICHELE:
For me, I always viewed the Edge
as an advantage.
It either, "A," gave me
an opportunity
to go back in the game,
or, "B," I knew that all of
my friends who were on the Edge
could give me advantages
or could come back in the game
and ultimately be
somebody who helps me.
So, everything great
that happened in my game
came from the Edge.
When you guys willed me
your fire tokens and allowed me
to buy advantages, it gave me
strength in this game.
I needed that
to carry me through.
And then Natalie coming back in
was like,
"Oh, my gosh.
I-I have a chance."
So, for me,
that was a complete opportunity.
And we worked through this game,
and that was the tightest
alliance I had at the end.
PROBST:
All right.
Let's move into the last phase.
Only one of you is going
to outlast the other two.
This is your last chance
to address this jury.
You've heard everything
they're curious about.
Is there anything left unsaid
to make sure you got it?
Natalie, go first.
(exhales)
So, my journey on Survivor was
a hand that I did not know
I was gonna be dealt.
And I think on Survivor,
half the battle is being able
to adapt and move on.
And when I came back in,
all I wanted to do was focus on
taking apart the alliance
that seemed like
they were unbreakable,
interjecting myself in there
and do what seemed impossible,
which was make it
all the way to the end
after getting voted out
freaking first.
I had the biggest target
on my back
after Chris came in last year
and made it to the final three.
Everybody said, "It's not
gonna happen this time around.
"You got back into the game,
and you made it to the end.
You basically have to play
a perfect game."
And, so,
I'm really proud of my game.
I'm really excited to be here.
And I... I...
Yeah. I'm really...
I'm really excited and proud,
and that's it.
(chuckles)
Michele.
Uh, so, my first season
was a lot different.
I only went
to six Tribal Councils.
That was a big question mark
for me.
Did I actually deserve that win?
On this season, I went
to 15 out of 19 Tribal Councils,
vulnerable through most of them,
my name on the block
for a lot of them.
And I worked a lot harder in
this season to get to the end.
I'm pretty proud of the way
that I played this game.
I think I played with integrity.
I think I made
a-a lot of great relationships.
I had advantages.
I had fire tokens.
So, I did play the best game
that I could possibly play for
the person who I am.
I'm not a beast
in challenges, you know,
and I can't build spy shacks;
it's not in my wheelhouse.
I'm pretty straightforward
and simple.
I played that game,
and I can look myself in the
mirror at the end of the day,
win or lose,
and be proud of that.
PROBST:
Tony.
All right.
Me, I came into this game
a totally different person.
I came as a human being.
I came as Tony.
I didn't come as the player that
you guys all seen on Cagayan.
From day one to day 38,
I played Survivor twice,
once during the day
and once at night.
Every single night, I was
out there looking for idols
because I couldn't do it
during the day.
I didn't want no target
on my back.
I told everybody, "Don't worry
about it." I'm awake,
so I'll feed the fire
so they can sleep.
I gridded the whole jungle
looking for the idols.
It took me 26 days to find one.
Um, the spy nest was very
helpful with my surveillance.
Everything I did,
I kept the target off my back.
I was leading votes
without people knowing
I was leading votes.
Natalie came in from Extinction.
She told everybody,
"Get rid of Tony.
Tony's got to go.
He's a big threat to win."
Uh, she was pushing the buttons,
and I still managed a way
to-to escape that.
Nobody ever put my name down
this game.
It was a tough battle
throughout.
I know it's a big, huge,
Super Bowl season of Survivor,
and I tried my best to be a-a
great player for this season.
And I hope you guys
could appreciate the hard work
I put into it
to get to where I am tonight.
DANNI:
I think all three of you guys
have had incredible journeys.
All different games.
But, honestly, in my eyes,
all three of you guys
have been incredible,
and that means a lot to us
as being winners along with you.
-Yep. Agreed.
-She speaks for all of us.
We have huge respect
for each and every journey
that got you here.
ADAM:
You guys should all be
incredibly proud
-of yourselves
for making it there.
-Yeah.
Something none of us could do.
And tonight, each and every one
of you has fought up here,
and it's making
all of our decisions...
-Awful.
-Really tough.
-...immensely difficult.
-Really, really hard.
ROB:
Because even though
some of us may have come in
with some ideas
of what we're gonna do,
tonight, you guys have
all showed why
each and every one of you
deserve to be up there.
-Yay! Good job!
-Yeah!
PARVATI:
So proud of you!
You guys deserve this.
PROBST:
Okay. Well, you guys have played
this game at a relentless pace,
and there is only one thing
left to do:
declare a victor of this war.
And that is in your hands.
Jury, I'm gonna give you a
moment, and then we will vote.
>> Probst: ALL RIGHT, IT IS
TIME TO BRING THE 40th
SEASON OF "SURVIVOR" TO A CLOSE.
JURY, IT'S TIME TO VOTE.
AMBER, YOU'RE UP.
>> OH, MAN.
♪
>> YOU'RE RIGHT, I SAID IF YOU
GOT BACK, YOU HAD TO PLAY
PERFECT.
YOU ALMOST DID.
YOU SHOULD HAVE TAKEN THIS GUY
OUT.
>> THIS IS SO HARD.
>> THIS IS THE SECOND TIME THAT
I'M WRITING YOUR NAME DOWN IN A
GAME, THE FIRST TIME I WROTE IT
DOWN TO VOTE YOU OUT, AND NOW I
AM VOTING FOR YOU TO WIN.
I'M SO PROUD OF YOU.
AND WHAT YOU HAVE ACCOMPLISHED.
SO YOU'RE AWESOME.
♪
>> I KNOW HOW HARD IT IS TO BE
JUST ON THE OUTS THE WHOLE TIME.
♪
>> Probst: I'LL GO GET THE
VOTES.
>> Probst: NATALIE, TONY,
MICHELE, JURY, I WILL SEE YOU
BACK IN LOS ANGELES FOR THE
READING OF THE VOTES.
♪
>> Probst: ALL RIGHT, I HAVE
THE VOTES.
WE HAVE THE FINAL THREE,
MICHELE, TONY, NATALIE.
CONGRATULATIONS ON A GREAT
SEASON.
AND I'M SORRY WE CAN'T BE
TOGETHER.
BUT I DO WANT TO SAY THIS:
REGARDLESS WHAT COMES FROM THIS
VOTE, I HOPE YOU WILL ALWAYS
REMEMBER YOU OUTLASTED 17 OF THE
BEST TO PLAY THIS GAME.
SO WIN OR LOSE, I HOPE YOU WILL
ALWAYS CELEBRATE THAT.
SO LET'S GET TO.
AND IF YOU HAVE FAMILY THAT ARE
ON THE CORNERS, BRING THEM IN.
THEY SHOULD BE A PART OF THIS.
BRING THEM INTO THE FRAME.
>> COME ON OVER HERE.
>> Probst: THERE'S TONY'S
FAMILY.
TONY, YOU'VE GOT MICHELE'S
SISTER.
SLIDE OVER, NATALIE.
A LITTLE MORE NATALIE.
THERE WE GO.
NATALIE'S BOYFRIEND.
LET'S PUT UP SOME MUSIC, JOE.
BECAUSE HERE'S THE TRUTH--
>> OH, MY GOD!
>> Probst: TWO OF YOU ARE
GOING TO LOSE.
THAT'S WHY IT'S SO VALUABLE AND
SO IMPORTANT WHEN YOU WIN.
IT MEANS SO MUCH.
ONE OF YOU IS GOING TO EARN $2
MILLION AND BECOME ONLY THE
SECOND TWO-TIME WINNER IN THE
HISTORY OF "SURVIVOR."
FOR THE FIRST TIME EVER, I'LL
READ THE VOTES FROM MY GARAGE.
>> OH, MY GOD!
>> Probst: HERE WE GO.
FIRST VOTE, TONY.
NATALIE.
ONE VOTE TONY, ONE VOTE NATALIE.
TWO VOTES NATALIE, ONE VOTE
TONY.
TIED AGAIN.
TWO VOTES TONY, TWO VOTES
NATALIE.
THREE VOTES NATALIE, TWO VOTES
TONY.
TIED AGAIN.
THREE VOTES TONY, THREE VOTES
NATALIE.
FOUR VOTES NATALIE, THREE VOTES
TONY.
WE'RE TIED AGAIN.
FOUR VOTES TONY, FOUR VOTES
NATALIE.
TONY.
THAT'S FIVE VOTES TONY, FOUR
VOTES NATALIE.
TONY.
THAT'S SIX VOTES TONY, FOUR
VOTES NATALIE.
SEVEN VOTES TONY, FOUR VOTES
NATALIE.
EIGHT VOTES TONY, FOUR VOTES
THE WINNER OF "SURVIVOR: WINNERS
AT WAR", TONY!
CONGRATULATIONS, TONY!
THERE'S OUR WINNER, AND THAT IS
THE TRUTH OF "SURVIVOR."
YOU HAVE THE AGONY OF DEFEAT,
AND YOU HAVE THE BEAUTIFUL WIN.
LET'S SEE THAT FAMILY BIG UP
THERE ON THE SCREEN.
TEAM TONY WITH HIS WIFE, TWO
KIDS.
IT'S SO HARD TO SAY GOODBYE TO
MICHELE AND NATALIE.
LET'S SEE HOW EVERYBODY VOTED.
YOU CAN SEE THERE WERE TWO
CAMPS.
NATALIE HAD FOUR PEOPLE WITH
HER, INCLUDING JEREMY, WHO WAS
LATE TO "THE EDGE."
AND EVERYBODY ELSE WAS FOR TONY.
AND DESPITE PLAYING THEIR HEARTS
OUT, THIS WAS A DOMINANT WIN,
TONY.
KIDS, IF I COULD JUST TALK TO
YOUR DAD A MINUTE.
REQUEST THE LITTLE BIT OF TIME
WE HAVE, TONY, HOW MUCH DOES THE
$2 MILLION CHANGE YOUR LIFE?
WE JUST HAVE A FEW SECONDS.
>> JEFF, IT'S LIFE CHANGINGSING,
ON IN THE WORLD, YOU SEE HOW
FINANCIAL SECURITY IS SO
IMPORTANT.
WITH THIS MONEY I'M GOING TO
MAKE SURE I SECURE MY FAMILY AND
BE FINANCIALLY SECURE FOR THE
REST OF MY LIFE.
>> Probst: TONY, I'M SORRY IT
WAS SO SHORT.
IT WAS AN EPIC FINALE.
YOU WERE A GREAT WINNER, A GREAT
REPRESENTATIVE OF OUR SHOW.
>> THANK YOU,.
>> Probst: I FEEL LIKE SUCH A
RUDE HOST.
HERE'S THE $2 MILLION CHECK.
LET'S TALK ABOUT OUR 41st
SEASON, BECAUSE NORMALLY WE SHOW
YOU A COOL PROMO.
FOR OBVIOUS REASONS WE HAVEN'T
BEEN ABLE TO SHOOT, BUT, MAN, WE
HAVE FUN IDEAS.
WE'RE ALWAYS TRYING TO EXPLORE
AND EVOLVE THE SHOW AND TAKE
CHANCES AND WE'RE GOING TO DO
THAT AND WE'RE COMMITTED TO
BEING ON THE FALL FOR OUR 41st
SEASON, WHICH MEANS YOU SHOULD
APPLY, FEPS YOU'RE YOUNG-- I'M
TALKING TEENAGERS, 6, 17, 18,
19.
DO IT.
COOL PARENTS AND A COOL SCHOOL,
WHO KNOWS IT COULD.
YOU CAN BID ON PROPS FOR THIS
SEASON, PROCEEDS GO TO STAND UP
TO CANCER, AND FEED AMERICA.
ON BEHALF OF OUR ENTIRE CREW,
400 PEOPLE, 25 COUNTRIES, WE
LOVE OUR JOBS.
WE'RE GOING TO COME TO YOU WITH
MORE "SURVIVOR."
THANK YOU, GOOD NIGHT, STAY
SAFE.
Captioned by
Media Access Group at WGBH
access.wgbh.org